Guide to the Edward Burne-Jones Letters to Cormell Price
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1854 March 9; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 23 x 37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Burne-Jones apologizes for being "forgetful" of Price and admits that he "cannot plead hard work altogether for my cause, so many nameless trifles occur all day long to break the best resolutions." He tells Price that he has heard that he is studying hard and wishes him success in his endeavors. He encourages Price to apply for an Oxford scholarship, noting that even in failure "the practice is very good and often encouraging." He says that this term has been his happiest yet and he has been filling his time with many good things. He admits that he has "fallen back upon my drawings and intend[s] cultivating it to some extent."
  Burne-Jones states that William Morris has taken up a lot of his time, describing him as "one of the cleverest fellows" he knows and "far more congenial in all his thoughts and likings, than anyone it has been [his] good fortune to meet with." He believes that Morris's art criticism is better than William Fulford's, who was Burne-Jones's "old ideal in such subjects." He proclaims that Morris is "full of enthusiasm for things holy and beautiful and true" and possesses "the most exquisite perception and judgement" which has "tinged [Burne-Jones's] whole inner being with the beauty of [Morris's] own." He remarks that "if it were not for his boisterous mad outbursts and freaks which break the romance [Morris] sheds [?] around him -- at least to me -- he would be a perfect hero."
  Burne-Jones asks Price to spend time with him at Easter. He says of Price's writing piece (presumably sent in correspondence from Price) that, unless it is for a joke, it is unlikely to be profitable. He asks him why he has written blank verse, remarking that the style "is a strange fashion of young poetlings of this generation; on the principle I suppose of the age generally 'as much as you can at the cheapest rate'." He also questions Price's "horticultural facts" and critiques his long preamble to the piece. He recommends that Price translates metrically from Greek lyrics, beginning with either Theocritus or the "chorus of the Dramatists."
  Date from postmark. The letter is dated by Burne-Jones: "March (?) 1854." Addressed from "Exeter Coll." Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) at "Classical Department, King Edward's School, Birmingham." With one penny stamp and wax seal. With cross writing on pages 2 -3.
  References: Georgiana Burne-Jones, v. 1, p. 95
  Correspondence; Poetry; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; University of Oxford; Morris, William, 1834-1896; Fulford, William, -1897
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1854 October 16; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 25 x 40 cm, folded to 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Burne-Jones says he would have written to Price earlier had he not had "too much friendship to pour my sorrows into your ear." He states that Price's last letter came at a time when he was "suffering greater mental troubles than [he] ever remember[s]."
  Burne-Jones complains about the postponement of the start of the university term, remarking that he "longed to be back with [William] Morris and his glorious little company of martyrs." Burne-Jones describes a recent evening party he attended and remarks upon the host's impropriety of offering a rose to "Fanny," noting "there is a language of flowers I hear, and you had better make it out, and see what he means."
  Burne-Jones tells Price about the time he has spent with his father and an upcoming visit from friends to their family home. Burne-Jones asks Price to let him know the details of his journey so that he can get settled into his room before Price's arrival.
  Addressed from "Bristol Road." Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) at "R. Price [illegible], Broadway, Gloucestershire." With one penny stamp and wax seal.
  Georgiana Burne-Jones, v. 1, p.p. 102-103
  Flower language; Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Morris, William, 1834-1896
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1856 January 9; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Burne-Jones asks why Price has not yet sent the "MS," presumably a piece for The Oxford and Cambridge Magazine. He tells him that Burne-Jones's aunt has been Price's "champion all along," transcribing a humorous conversation he had with her at breakfast the previous day, in which Burne-Jones describes Price as a "reprobate" and "a dissolute little creature" while "Auntie" defends him as a "dear little fellow." Burne-Jones says he does not want to hurry Price over the magazine but that they should "make a work of it, and not a mere pastime." Burne-Jones instructs Price to send his piece to him.
  He laments a previous issue's article on Charles Kingsley, saying that although the group plans to amend the piece in future copies of the article, it has "already done us a great deal of harm, especially in the Universities." He notes that Harry MacDonald has sent a "very severe letter" to Wilfred Heeley about the matter.
  Burne-Jones states that William Morris (referred to here as "Topsy") has passed on editorship powers to William Fulford, remarking that the move "will be a good thing for all of us, and a great relief to Topsy." He describes a dinner he had with Morris and MacDonald at Brompton which he says was "like old times." Burne-Jones gleefully comments that he will "get an awful showing up in the Guardian ... for that wretched affair on Kingsley." He ends by telling Price about an upcoming boxing match (?), which he says will be followed by a "general challenge to Universal Pigdom, for the championship -- odds, Ten to one, on the side of Truth and, O.C.M."
  Addressed from "Camberwell."
  References: Georgiana Burnes-Jones, v. 1, p. 127
  Oxford and Cambridge magazine; Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Fulford, William, -1897; Heeley, Wilfred, 1833-1876; Kingsley, Charles, 1819-1875; Macdonald, Henry James, 1835-1891; Morris, William, 1834-1896
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1856 May 18; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 21 x 27 cm, folded to 21 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Burne-Jones begins the letter with the following declaration: "Mr Jones begs respectfully to inform the public that he executes pictures of the most chaste and unique description upon the most reasonable terms." He then lists prices for a variety of types of drawings, including "love scenes, executed in bold style, indian ink" (5 shillings) and "full length caricature" (2 shillings and sixpence). He goes on to announce that he is "desirous of forming classes for the reading of Ruskin." Burne-Jones says that if Price were in London, he would see the streets "placarded" with such announcements before he gives up the joke, commenting "no you wouldn't, what lies I tell."
  Burne-Jones says he is "desolate" because William Fulford has "gone to Hill's" for a few days. He says that he has taken a 12-mile walk in the rain and plans to "write letters and be miserable" for the rest of the day or "go and join the mob in Hyde Park." He asks Price to write to him often and to encourage Charlie Faulkner and "Dickides" (Richard Watson Dixon?) to do the same.
  Burne-Jones says he has received a note from "Topsy" (William Morris) recommending that he see Arthur Hughes's April Love. Burne-Jones says he plans to visit the Royal Academy the following morning to see it. He asks Price to give Morris his love. Burne-Jones offers his love to "all the set" and sketches a heart surrounded by their names (Willie, Harry, Dickides, Hatch, Charlie, Puckle, Oakley and Guest) so that Price "forget[s]none." Sketch measures 5 x7 cm.
  Addressed from "13 Sloane Terrace, Sloane St, Chelsea." In the top left hand corner of the letter, Burne-Jones has sketched a hand with its index finger pointing right, towards his Sloane Terrace address. Sketch measures 2 x 5 cm.
  Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Dixon, Richard Watson, 1833-1900; Faulkner, Charles Joseph, 1833-1892; Fulford, William, -1897; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Morris, William, 1834-1896; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1856 May 30; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 25 x 40 cm, folded to 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Burne-Jones says that he owes Price more apologies than he has time to write at present. He tells Price he has taken rooms at Old House, Ship Street in Oxford and asks that Price tells him which train he will take to Oxford so that Burne-Jones can meet him.
  Burne-Jones goes on to give Price details about gaining entry to New College, remarking that on Sunday morning it is hosting a private party and admission will not be possible. He recommends that Price asks the sub-warden -- rather than the chaplain or one of the Fellows -- for tickets if his party is more than two.
  Burne-Jones asks his friend not to think him too unkind for responding to two letters from Price with such a short reply. He asks Price what he means by "Cupids less [?] -- a secret, eh? -- we must get it out of you." He ends by asking Price to remember him kindly to his sisters and assuring Price that he thinks he stands "a very good chance."
  Addressed from "Exeter Coll." Addressed to Price (on outer leaf) at "8 Sun St. West, Birmingham." With one penny stamp and wax seal.
  Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; University of Oxford
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1856 June 15; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 37 cm, folded to 23 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Burne-Jones sends his best wishes for Price's recovery from a bout of illness, remarking that he "daren't tell Auntie about it, or she'd be hurrying off to nurse [Price]." He asks if Price could stay in Birmingham for the first three days of the following week as Burne-Jones will be visiting his father and would like to see Price, commenting that "it seems generations past since [they] had one of those dear evenings."
  Burne-Jones says that he is happier than he has ever been which he follows with the observation that "Art does seem so precious to one, so inexpressibly lovely." He says he is much less lonely now that William Fulford has returned, saying that few people ever visit his rooms, noting that "Fred" only comes in for breakfast from time to time and that "Harry" Macdonald "prefers the company of ladies, so [Burne-Jones] seldom see[s] him." Burne-Jones says he does not enjoy dinner, as he has to walk to a "chop-house, which smells of never-ending ever-wasting joints" and where other customers "monopolise the papers."
  Addressed from "13 Sloane Terrace."
  Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Fulford, William, -1897; Macdonald, Henry James, 1835-1891
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1861 June 28; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 2 folded sheets (8 pages): autograph letter, signed; both sheets 21 x 27 cm, folded to 21 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Burne-Jones says he has been a "villain" in his lack of correspondence with Price and says that the rest of the day will be given over to writing him letters, remarking that although the letter will only take half an hour to write, "the exertion will completely do for [him]." He asks if Price is "lonely out there" and says he has encouraged William Morris to write to him and will try to get "everyone" to do the same. He says they will all be so glad when Price comes back.
  Burne-Jones has been doing "heaps of work" but admits that when the summer days get hot, he will not work as much. He tells Price that Charles Faulkner will be moving from Oxford to London this month. He says that "there has been such a fire here in London" [referring to the Tooley Street Fire], stating that one could see it from thirty miles away.
  Burne-Jones asks Price if he has heard of the "Co." (Morris, Marshall, Faulkner & Co.), stating it has been founded by himself, "Topsy" (William Morris), Marshall, Brown, Webb and Rossetti. He tells Price that they produce "stained glass, furniture, jewelry, decorations and pictures," noting that they have many commissions already.
  Burne-Jones describes the ordeal of a friend (probably Elizabeth Siddal) whose baby was stillborn, commenting that the mother is physically better but mourns for her child. Burne-Jones gives an account of his and Price's mutual friends, remarking that Ford Madox Brown is "fat and cheery" and that he sees Richard Watson Dixon about once a year. Burne-Jones does not approve of Dixon's marriage to Maria Sturgeon, the widow of William Thomson of Haddingtonshire, describing Sturgeon as "an old dry coquettish hag."
  On page four, Burne-Jones admits that the first three pages of the letter were written three months ago. He asks Price to forgive him his silence and says he had a dream where Price would not speak to him because he had not written in so long. He says that not much has happened in the intervening period but that he has run in to trouble in the wake of Thomas Edward Plint's death, as Burne-Jones owed him £550. He comments that Elizabeth Barrett Browning has died, describing her as "the cleverest woman alive." Burne-Jones says that there have more murders and fires in London, putting the spate down to "that bloody comet," a reference to the Great Comet of 1861. Burne-Jones tells Price that he and his wife (Georgiana MacDonald) are expecting a baby but pleads with Price not to tell anyone "for fear it should be a monster." He gives further account of there mutual friends, telling Price that Charlie Faulkner has moved to London to work as a civil engineer, that Rossetti has "done a most wonderful picture," that Alice Prinsep is to "marry a rich cove" and that Val Prinsep has returned from Italy, "leaving many broken hearts."
  Burne-Jones gives Price his new address in Great Russell Street, commenting that his studio there is much better than his last. Burne-Jones apologizes profusely for not writing and sends love to Price from both himself and Georgiana. He talks of his plans to take her to Italy, if the baby is well enough to be left. He says he will not be able to get home to Birmingham until Christmas. Burne-Jones talks of his desire to move his father closer to London as he is growing old. He reflects upon fatherhood, writing "it's very dull to be a dad, and having a son cuttting about & enjoying himself ... I shall hate it when I'm a dad."
  References: Georgiana Burne-Jones, v. 1, p. 227, 229
  Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Faulkner, Charles Joseph, 1833-1892; Brown, Ford Madox, 1821-1893; Burne-Jones, Georgiana, Lady, 1840-1920; Dixon, Richard Watson, 1833-1900; Morris, Marshall, Faulkner & Company; Morris, William, 1834-1896; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Siddall, Elizabeth
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1862 February 23; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 21 x 27 cm, folded to 21 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Burne-Jones thanks Price for his last letter, commenting that it has been passed around and shared with "all who want [Price] back." He pleads with Price to move back to Britain, offering Price a room in his home until he can find something permanent. He tells Price his family are spending three months in Venice from May and that Price could have their home in London to himself.
  Burne-Jones tells Price that Elizabeth Siddall has died and that Rossetti is "smashed for the time." He says it is his aunt's birthday and that she is grateful for Price's letter. Burne-Jones reports that his wife and son are well, describing his son as "the fattest boy ... known to Art or nature." He proceeds with a lengthy describe of his son, of whom his parents are "very proud." He tells Price that Jane Burden Morris, wife of William Morris, is expecting twins.
  Burne-Jones says that George Price Boyce is in Cairo and that Hughes (Arthur?) had become father to twins, when last Burne-Jones heard from him. He also describes their friends "Dickides" (Richard Watson Dixon?), Val Prinsep, Ford Madox Brown, William Fulford and Charles Faulkner. Burne-Jones pleads again with Price to come back to live near them all, and describes the excellent location of their house in London to encourage Price to reside there. He describes the seduction techniques employed by their friend William Fulford, who "develop[s] [women] into adoration of him and leaves them to pine."
  Burne-Jones ends by encouraging Price to come back and giving Price Burne- Jones's infant son's "fat little dumpy slobbery love."
  Addressed from "62 Great Russell St."
  References: Georgiana Burne-Jones, v. 1, p. 259
  Correspondence; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898 -- Correspondence; Price, Cormell, approximately 1836-1910 -- Correspondence; Brown, Ford Madox, 1821-1893; Dixon, Richard Watson, 1833-1900; Faulkner, Charles Joseph, 1833-1892; Fulford, William, -1897; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Siddall, Elizabeth
- Edward Burne-Jones letter to Cormell Price, 1862 June 3; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter, signed; 21 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
  "Dearest Crom, I won't write at length; you may never get this -- we shall be in Venice I hope in a week to stop there for nearly a month, direct poste restante. I do do hope we shall meet this year. Love from Georgie. Most affectionately yours, Ned."
  Arrangement
  Addressed from "Milan."